<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org">
<title>Design of the toc for RDA</title>
<para>

The idea is that we don't have to read the entire contents of an RDA
file into memory just to see what variables are there or then discard
the elements we don' want.  Instead, we should be able get a table of
contents from the RDA file without consuming the memory to store the
values.  The format does not allow us to quickly jump from one element
to the next.  When we an encounter the start of an element, i.e. the
name, we then have to read the resulting object to find the start of
the next element.  What we can do however is not create the object in
memory but discard the content.  And further, we can determine the
offset within the file, i.e. the number of bytes, at which each
element starts.  Then we can return to the RDA file and jump directly
to the particular elements we want.  So we want to be able to compute
the offset table.

</para>

<para>
We could define a new format which adds the table
of contents to the end of the file.
By putting the size of the table of contents at 
the very end of the file, we can 
then identify the table of contents quickly
and further more append to the file. 
Replacing an existing element is harder.
</para>
<para>
See how this has been done in other approaches
such as using a database (gdbm?), writing to separate
files on disk (Brahm from MIT? RObjectTables)
</para>
<para>
http://tolstoy.newcastle.edu.au/R/e2/help/07/05/16594.html
</para>
<section>
<title>Details &amp; Notes</title>
<para>
The are REFSXP with the index in the value or following it
as a separate integer.
</para>
<para>
A degenerate function of the form
<r:code>
function(){}
</r:code>
appears to have a tag as well as an attribute.
But the attributes flag is part of the packing.
</para>
<para>
For a package environment (e.g. on a function)
write out a flag PACKAGESXP and the name of the package as a string.
</para>
<para>
For namespace environments, write a flag NAMESPACESXP
and the name of the environment as a string.
</para>
</section>
</article>